[Music]
hi everyone this is Ravi welcome to
tricentis tasa Advanced Training as you
all know I already published 70 YouTube
videos covering beginners level
intermediate level and Advan level
concepts of prent tasa test automation
from QV videos onwards I've started
teaching you the realtime scenarios
where you might encounter different
types of obstacles and how can we solve
those obstacles while automating your
test
cases so this is our lesson
71 in terms of overall tricentis tasa
Advanced Training and this is our lesson
29 are obstacle 29 in terms of real time
scenarios please do subscribe to the
channel click on Bell icon you'll
receive notifications whenever I publish
more videos thank
you in this lesson I'm going to teach
you how can you solve an obstacle where
you need to interact with the
application and you need to enter the
long day or the full name of the
we or the full name of of the week day
of future date by using date expression
with the help of tricentis tasa so now
let us go and see the obstacle in detail
what is the problem that we need to
solve
for so this is our obstacle the name of
the obstacle is future Christmas and
which is categorized as easy let us go
for
it so it says you need to calculate on
which day Christmas Falls in 2
years WR it as a word like Monday so
let's
assume our 25th December
2025 falls on
Thursday but we need to calculate which
day of the Christmas
Falls after 2 years that means
your
2027 2627 so in the year
2027 the Christmas falls on which day so
in
2027 the Christmas falls on
Saturday see that means you have solved
your automation problem successfully so
how can I calculate
the day of the
Christmas that falls in 2 years so let
us go to
triena and let us automate this
scenario as usual we're going to capture
the objects or elements of the
application under
modules so this is the folder that we
are capturing obstacles folder under
obstacles folder right click on this
obstacles folder select scan
application and then select the
application that you would like to scan
and click on
scan so you can see here now we need to
enter the full day of
weekday in this edit box so that's why
I'm going to
select the edit box enter the day so
this is the only object that we need to
automate this scenario and then I'm
going to name the module with the
obstacle number copy
this and paste it
here so you can see this enter the day
edit box is uniquely identified so done
now let us save the
module and close the X
scan so let's go back to trient
tasa you can see here the new obstacle
that we captured this is the new
obstacle that we have this is our new
obstacle so now let us go to the left
section let us go to the left section
test case section so here under folder
obstacles let me create a new new test
case right click on this obstacles
folder and
then select create test
case name this as same as the obstacle
number and now double click on this test
case so let us automate the test case to
automate the test case we need to drag
and drop your module onto your test case
and now let us expand this one so here
we need to
calculate the day on which the Christmas
Falls in 2 years so for that let us go
to
Trenta so here so there is one function
called L day
inasa so to call any function you need
to open curly braces now type l d a see
you can see here now L Day Day according
to the current system settings so what
is the syntax to calculate the long day
you need to enter the
date and then your offset and then in
which format you need the output so
basically L day your date expression
your offset and then your format
so this is the format so what I'm going
to do here l d a y now let us write the
expression within the square braces and
close curly braces so here first you
need to enter your date expression open
curly
braces
date and what is the date I would like
to
enter current year Christmas date that
is is
25 do 12 do
2025 this is my current year Christmas
date and now what is your offset my
offset is 2 years because I need to
calculate
from I need to calculate the Day falls
in 2 years right so I'm going to put a
I'm going to enter the offset as place
to y and then what is the format that
you need I don't want to enter any
format because I need a full day that's
it I don't want to change the format
this expression by default gives you the
full name of the weekday right so once
that is done close curly
braces so here now let me explain again
what we have done L day is a function
which returns
the full name of the week day so here I
have entered the date expression where I
have entered the date of this year
Christmas and then I'm providing the
offset of offset as 2 years that means
it's going to return the full name of
the week day for the Christmas date in
the year 2027
right so once that is done so now let
us run this test case and see if it
works correctly so let me change the
work state to
completed and save the test case let's
go back to our
application let's click on try again now
let's run the test case in scratchbook
right click and run in
scratchbook it should enter the four
full day of Christmas in the year
2027 which is
Saturday yep see you can see here now it
entered Saturday that means our test
case is passed so if you want to
understand if it is calculating
correctly or not before even you run the
test case what you need to do you have
to come back to your prent Taska
there is another way right click on this
and you can select translate value this
way you can understand if it is
calculating the correct day or not so
you can see the output value is Saturday
let's do one thing let me do one thing
okay so let me do one thing if I want to
calculate the day of
Christmas in the next here I'm going to
put it as + 1 y let's translate this
right
click right click and then translate
value it should be Friday this is Friday
which is correct and let's say if I want
to calculate this here what is the I can
just remove the offset okay I'm just
calculating the day of this date this
year Christmas date right click
translate value it should be Thursday
right so this is how you can calculate
the day of weekday for any given date so
if you have any queries leave your
queries in the comment box I'll try to
respond to your queries please do
subscribe to the channel click on Bell
icon you'll receive notifications
whenever I publish more videos don't
forget to like and share the video thank
you
[Music]